the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet with zero
holography
[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank de Freitas
and welcome to another week of holotalk
for the week of October 11
1999. a little bit of a different type
of program this week we're going to take
a look at a new process that was sent to
me from Jeff Blythe in the UK who was
working with a number of different
people on this project in creating your
own holographic plates this is a very
interesting process it could turn out to
be a wonderful experiment for those
already working with holography and
seems to have hit a dead end or maybe
looking for something interesting to do
that's completely new and a new
direction for them and the plates seem
wonderful and the the results compared
to traditional commercially available
materials and also the fact that they
are paying chromatic which means that
they can be exposed with several
different wavelengths such as your uh
your red lasers your helium neon your
laser pointers your laser diodes and
also into the green
an argon laser handy or even want to
begin experimenting with the green laser
pointers as well so we're going to be
taking a look at this entire process a
little bit later on in the show and I've
also included information in the actual
papers that have been published on this
on the website so you'll see links for
those as well and you might want to
click on those links and print out that
information and begin the process
yourself I've had an opportunity to look
over the material so I printed them out
and before I began the show I started to
uh to go over them and it it looks like
a relatively easy process and it's it's
something I'm going to look into and
perhaps even begin to coat my own
holographic place wouldn't that be
wonderful to be able to make your own
holographic plates inexpensively
especially the larger size of such as
eight by tens or 30 by 40 centimeter
glass plates make up your own emulsions
and put them onto the plates and uh
wind up having your own hologram now
that is an entire great process from
start to finish your own homemade
holographic lab
and your own holographic plates so this
is a very exciting bit of information
it's just come down the pike from Jeff
and we're going to take a look at that
in just a moment I wanted to thank
everyone who came to the open house last
actually it's Wednesday evening we had
about 12 or 13 people that stopped by
along with their children
and we had a great time here in the lab
I started that explaining a little bit
about the new diode lasers and we passed
traditional laser tubes around and
learned how traditional gas healing neon
lasers worked and then I passed the
little diodes around and the circuits
that go along with them explained how
the diodes work and how it's changing
the face of holography
and then we came down in the lab and one
of the things that everyone had an
opportunity to see were a nice laser
transmission Holograms which people
normally don't get an opportunity to see
outside of a laboratory environment so
everyone was real happy to see those and
they're they're wonderful Holograms I
love laser transmission Holograms I
always have and I always will they're
they're the best Holograms to me and I
always like to see people's reaction
when they walk up to a laser
transmission hologram and they take
their hand and reach around and try and
manipulate the different objects that
are appearing behind the plate and their
hands just passed through air so I took
some pictures and I'm not thinking I
should have done the digital camera I'm
taking a few pictures with the digital
camera but I took it with the
traditional film so I guess the film
will sit in the camera until a birthday
comes along or something like that and I
get the film to them but I'd like to
point out that the next open house will
be Wednesday November 3rd at 7 30 pm and
you're welcome to come out to the studio
and enjoy some snacks and coffee and
soda hear a little bit about holography
and come down into the studio and see
some pretty amazing Holograms that I
have here in my own personal collection
that I've managed to collect over the
years
so let's take a quick break and I'll be
right back and we're going to start
talking about how to make your own
holographic plates I'll be right back
would you like to create your own
three-dimensional Holograms well you can
begin today and Frankie Freitas can show
you how
from introductory guy shulock
philography system to developing
Innovative and affordable new laser
systems along with year-round holography
Workshop programs Frank is finding a way
to bring the attic reach into the reach
of everyone from September through May
you can attend Monica's free evening
lecture series at the studio in
Allentown Pennsylvania which is a quick
non-stop drive from the New York
Philadelphia Baltimore and Washington DC
areas offered the first Wednesday of
every month Frankie
evening at 7 30 with a talking
holography followed by a tour of the
labs and a chance to view Holograms in
his personal collection there is no cost
to attend the Wednesday evening lecture
but you must call in advance or send an
email to make reservations
to reach the studio for more information
we can make reservations for the
Wednesday evening lecture series please
call toll-free 1-800-458-3
5 or send an email from the website that
number again is
1-800-458-3525 to attend the Wednesday
evening lecture at the studio Frank
hopes to see you there
thank you
okay let's Jump Right In the title of
the paper is a diffusion method for
making silver bromide based holographic
recording material
the authors Jeff Blythe
Roger B Millington Andrew G Mayes
and Christopher R Lowe Institute of
biotechnology University of Cambridge
and I certainly hope I pronounced all of
the names correctly
the paper appeared in the Imaging
science journal volume 47 Pages
87-91
1999 and I am not absolutely certain if
that is a past issue of this year a
current issue of this year or will be a
future issue of this year so those of
you who are subscribers to the Imaging
science journal
we'll know that right off the bat volume
47 if that is a past issue current or
future issue in any case what I'd like
to do is uh just cover the abstract and
introduction here with you now and
following that I would also like to just
go over the technique a little bit and
once again these papers are available on
the website if you go onto the whole
talk page you'll see the links click on
those links and it will take you to the
pages you can print them out
one page is the abstract introduction
and the actual article and the second
page is the technique
so you'll have to come back to the whole
talk page to go from one page to another
let's start off with the abstract
a simple diffusion method for the
distribution of ultra fine silver
bromide grains in pre-coated gelatin and
customized polymeric films for
holographic recording has been developed
method involves two steps
immersion of the pre-formed film and a
solution of a silver salt followed by
agitation of the film in a solution of a
bromide salt containing sensitizing dye
repetition of the operation on the same
film with different sensitizing dyes in
the bromide bath enables the production
of a film with panchromatic response
transmission electron microscopy
reveals a grain structure very suitable
for use in holography a reflection
hologram made by this method has very
similar brightness under the same
exposure and processing conditions to
one made from a proprietary hologram
recording material currently available
now this is fascinating stuff folks to
be able to make your own holographic
plate be able to control what wavelength
the plate is sensitive to or having it
possibly sensitive to both
wavelengths of both red and green and
having the final results
very similar in in
quality two materials that you're paying
for
and possibly exceeding let's not leave
that out I'm sure as people begin
working with this they will find ways of
actually taking it to another level as
well let's move on to the uh
introduction
the original method conceived by Gabriel
Lipman over a century ago to produce the
first filterless color photographs used
in the constructive interference of each
wavelength in the white light when it
was returned from a reflective surface
in Intimate contact with the emulsion
the system gained a somewhat notorious
reputation for making difficult demands
on makers of silver halide emulsions the
emotions needed to be both exclusively
of ultra fine grain and panchromatic
such fine-grained emulsions have seen a
Renaissance in the last 30 years with
the development of holography since the
grain sizes for both techniques are
comparable
however commercially available silver
haline emulsions materials intended for
holography have been restricted to a
relatively narrow band photosensitivity
and have been generally unsuitable for
the much more stringent demands of
lipmann's photographic method
the long-held impression that the
fabrication of do-it-yourself Litman
emulsions is not for the faint-hearted
may still linger consequently there is a
need for the introduction of a simple
technique for making Ultra fine-grained
emulsions
this paper describes a diffusion method
for producing a holographic recording
material which avoids the traditional
laborious Emulsion forming methods for
producing silver bromide in gelatin and
films light sensitive ultra fine silver
bromide grains can be introduced into
thin films of a number of natural or
synthetic polymers even if they are
somewhat hydrophobic
these polymers may be preformed or
polymerized in sutu by UV ear radiation
on a suitable substrate sorry about that
folks I had to flip the paper here it
has recently been pointed out to us by
Hans belchagen that this diffusion
method is a variation of one used in
Germany some 85 years ago and claimed to
give extraordinarily fine grain for the
lipmann photographic process
okay then it goes on to the experimental
section where it mentions the materials
hang along with me here pancromatic
sense of the sensitation
conclusions
okay captions credits let's move on to
the actual technique
once again all this material is
available on the website
okay this would be the one which is um
second piece of information the second
link there
and this is the preparation
a simple way to make silver halide
hologram recording plates by diffusion
what follows is in the form of a
worksheet based on the paper published
in the Imaging science journal volume 47
page 87-91 1999 and this is the
worksheet.html on the website let's go
through the materials number one
pre-subbed glass plates and it mentions
here you can use the old holographic
plates with the gelatin removed with the
aid of household bleach which I've done
on numerous occasions just take your
or other plates put them into a little
bath
with some regular Clorox bleach in there
and you'll see that Emulsion will just
dissolve right into the Clorox bleach
take the plate out rinse it under water
and you've got a beautifully uh clean
piece of flat glass
and if you've got as many Holograms
sitting around that didn't work out as I
do from all that experiment and all the
experiments with the laser pointers and
diodes I've got plenty plenty plenty
plenty of
old holographic plates that I can
convert believe me number two gelatin of
Bloom strength now Bloom strength is in
quotes and I'm not quite sure what that
is it's a learning process for me as
well here this is brand new
a blue strength between 250 and 300.
and it gives a little bit more
information on that there as well on the
papers you'll see on the website and in
parentheses it says you can use culinary
gelatin without any sugar or flavorings
chemicals let's go down a list of
ascorbic acid or vitamin C
silver nitrate
lithium bromide
chromium acetate
and if you've got your sensitizing dies
here as well different dyes for
different wavelengths
sodium hydroxide and a number nine here
says in parentheses for new glass plates
and it's got a chemical there which I
will not even attempt to try and
pronounce the name
here
so let's move on you'll see it on the uh
on the page I won't even give it an
attempt
concentration of solutions
quantities will need to be judged by you
to suit your requirements
and that goes on to how you mix all of
these things together
that whole section here preparation of
plates glass plates usually need a
pre-treatment step or the gelatin
coating may peel off you can use old
holographic plates by simply giving them
a 10 minute soak and neat domestic
bleach solution and then rub off the old
gelatin layer under tap water
after a final link to distilled water no
further subbing set is usually required
step
however with freshly cut glass plates I
leave them soaking overnight in a strong
10 percent caustic soda solution to both
degrease them and activate the surface
don't do this without eye protection and
thick rubber gloves a splashing this
dangerous liquid is almost always
unavoidable so that's another thing we
need to keep in mind folks
as you look at this and if you're a
school an educator or someone that's
working in your home
et cetera Etc please keep in mind the
requirements and safety requirements of
working with all the materials that are
stated in any of the uh any of the
materials that you're going to find out
for this and take the necessary
precautions for your safety at all times
they're then washed and distilled water
and dried
after the plates are dry I rubbed them
over with a one percent solution of
three oh there's that chemical there's
that chemical they're trying to get me
to say this no matter how hard I try not
to and maybe I should just give it a
shot three Amino
property propyl tri-ethoxaline
ooh
good Lord in acetone on tissue until it
has evaporated and leave them in air to
interact now I'm getting stuck on the
small words and leave them in air to
interact with the saline for at least
two hours before coating
preparation of coding solution for an 8
by 10 inch plate excuse me
add 30 grams gelatin to 170 milliliters
cold water and mark the liquid level on
the beaker Place Beaker in a water bath
and heat while stirring constantly until
gelatin solution is between 70 and 80
degrees Celsius
stir until all granules have cleared top
up level to the mark
to remove skin and surface bone pour
through a fine mesh nylon stockings work
fine into a preheated beaker
then immediately proceed to The Next
Step which is coding by the old
Victorian curtain method
hold the beaker in your right hand and
with your left hand incline the
pre-subbed glass plate preheated to
around 60 degrees Celsius at an angle of
about 30 degrees to the vertical with
its bottom Edge in a clean tray
pour the gelatin in a line about one
centimeter from the top of the plate
lung rate must be continuous until the
furthest edge of the plate is reached
and in parentheses it says you may have
to accept the tendency of the coating to
not completely cover the lower part
closest to the furthest Edge
lean the plate against something for a
few minutes while coating gels
run a knife along thick layer at the
bottom to free plate rather than risk
tearing the delicate coating I guess
once you have that coated it becomes
thicker and you don't want to just lift
that plate up you want to take a little
exacto blade or razor blade or a sharp
knife and go along that bottom Edge to
cut it free
and in parentheses since no hardener is
involved yet the gel can be readily
scooped up and recoated if you are not
satisfied isn't this cool isn't this
cool I think there's a lot of people
that are going to have success with this
boy this is exciting stuff
wow
put plate in cold solution of chromium
acetate for one minute shake off drips
and then without washing away that salt
blow plate with a cold air
once the layer is dry leave the plate to
complete the Chrome hardening effect
overnight in a warmer preferably of
around 60 degrees Celsius for several
hours
rinse the hardened plate in distilled
water and dry in a warm airflow
if you want to cut plate up for next
step after scowling scoring the glass on
the back and cracking it it is best not
to pull sections apart before running a
scaffold blade along the gelatin side
first so that it is cut and not torn
apart once again similar to taking the
plate out of that that coating bath if
you're going to score and cut the plates
just don't cut the glass side and then
pull them apart you might want to score
and cut the gel also and have a clean
cut on the gelatin side as well which I
think that it's getting at
okay the loading operation silver
bromide loading operation and we're
getting close to the end here
we have four four by five inch plate
Place approximately three milliliters
six percent silver nitride solution in
the center and at once squash it with a
clean flat cover plate preferably
transparent plastic so that you can see
air bubbles are squeezed out leave for
three minutes safe lighting is not
necessary here but the lighting should
be subdued
remove cover plate and immediately
remove the excess silver Solution on its
surface by gently brushing over the
plate with the edge of a piece of filter
paper
blow dry plate with cool air and under
safe flight conditions add 2.5
milliliter of dye solution per 100
milliliter of lithium bromide solution
add about 0.2 milliliter of one percent
ascorbic acid solution and this is the
same solution as used in the final
sensitizing bath to agitate the bath and
plunge plate in while maintaining the
agitation for about four minutes
and number six is wrench rinse well
under running tap water
and in parentheses it says any any
bromide only on the surface can be
removed by gently rubbing with ungloved
finger plates usually come out of this
bath beautifully clear under the green
safe light without any special surface
deposit
final step sensitizing bath step the
plate can be immersed for one minute and
one percent ascorbic acid solution
adjusted to pH 5 using a little Soviet
sodium carbonate or hydroxide
alternatively the well-known
triathanolamine pre-swelling technique
can be used with the advantage of
increasing brightness at a shorter
wavelength and once again in parentheses
prolonged settling period May then be
necessary however to avoid creep while
the
electric is being made
after exposure the plate is then treated
conventionally how about that isn't that
fantastic this is wonderful stuff
so that's going to be it for the show
I'm not going to take it any further
you've got your homework there you've
got a lot of research and reading to do
with the materials that are up on the
website so if anyone gives it a shot
could you please send me an email I'd
love to hear if even if you're only
thinking about doing it and you've heard
the show and you want to try it send me
an email let me know and we'll keep in
touch and find out how this turns out
but when did wouldn't this be fantastic
if all of us start making our own
holographic plates this is great stuff
all right folks we've got guests coming
up the next couple weeks in fact I'm
going to record a number of shows this
upcoming week and just stack them
together and use them week by week so
don't forget to tune in each and every
week for hollow talk and this is Frankie
Freitas take care and I'll see you next
week